# Kiprono Elijah Koech | Résumé

Nairobi, Kenya

in: https://www.linkedin.com/in/kipronokoech

## Summary

Highly analytical, ingenious and results-oriented data scientist and statistician focusing on being a grounded researcher providing solutions to real-world problems through data analysis and modelling. Possessing working knowledge of Python programming and database management using SQL with the application in predictive modelling and data analysis, among other areas.

### Key Skills

Areas of Expertise

Applied Statistics Machine Learning Deep Learning

Computer Vision

Data Mining

Data Visualization

Reproducible Research

Business Intelligence and Analytics

**Applied Mathematics** 

Database Management

Tools and Technologies.

Git Version Control

R (familiar)

**LATEX** 

TensorFlow and Keras

AWS

HTML and CSS

Tableau Microsoft Office Suite

Docker

**SPSS** Linux Looker

Soft skills...

Python

Dependable

Very quick and eager to learn

Thriving in solving complex tasks

Excellent Communicator

#### **Education**

**Stellenbosch University** 

Certificate: Master's Degree in Applied Mathematics (Data Science)

Feb 2020 - Apr 2022

Cape Town, South Africa

Research area: Deep Learning/ Computer vision

Stellenbosch University

Certificate: Master's Degree in Mathematical Sciences, Cum Laude

Cape Town, South Africa Jan 2019 - Nov 2019

Research area: Machine Learning and Computer Vision

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology

Certificate: Bachelor's Degree in Science (Statistics), First Class Honors

Nairobi, Kenya Sep 2013 - Nov 2017

#### **Work Experience**

#### Data Intelligence Analyst, Sun King Limited

Nairobi, Kenya

A brief: Analyzing data to drive sales and improve collection of follow-on revenues.

January 2023 - To Date

• Design pilots, analyze data and make recommendations to help improve sales of our products and promote collection of follow-on revenues on products under loan.

### Data Science Intern, Kenya Meteorological Department

Nairobi, Kenya

A brief: Working on techniques to improve weather forecasting.

April 2022 - October 2022

- Working on improving weather forecasting through application of machine learning recurrent neural network models,
- Testing new parametrization schemes, and,
- Optimizing data assimilation procedures for Weather Research and Forecasting (WRF) model initialization.

### Research Fellow, Science of Intelligence

Berlin, Germany

A brief: Worked on a computer vision project at Technische Universität Berlin.

Feb 2021 - Aug 2021

Worked on action recognition problem for wildlife

## Data Science Technical Mentor, Great Learning - Olympus

(Remote) Texas, U.S.A Nov 2020 - Aug 2021

A brief: A mentorship and tutoring role for data science students.

Mentored and tutored 6 students per semester taking a course in Data Science and Business Analytics at Olympus,

attaining 100% successful completion of the course.

#### Data Assistant, PACT-Timiza

Kisii and Migori, Kenya

A brief: Data entry, management and analysis role involving HIV patients information.

Jan 2018 - Dec 2018

- Managed HIV patients data for over 10,000 clients. This involved entering information on the paper into the IQ care database; analyze the data to locate clients with poor adherence and recommend follow-up; and data quality checks.
- Follow-up reduced the cases of poor adherence to anti-retroviral by over 70% and be able to close cases as required. Rectified an event that almost led to the loss of 2300 data points due to system failure. The by-product of this was setting up a more robust backup pipeline.
- Worked as a Data Clerk for the first 2 months then promoted to Data Assistant.

### Statistician Intern, South Nyanza (SONY) Sugar Company

Migori, Kenya

A brief: An internship working with factory data in a sugar company.

Jun 2017 - Dec 2017

- Analyzed factory data to explain production trends and seasonality phenomena.
- Particularly analyzed downtime data and reported variables that are most significant in impacting the extent of downtime. Upon implementation, there was a 42% drop in downtime in 2018 compared to 2017.

### **Projects**

- 1. Fruit Detection | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
  - In this project, Mask R-CNN and YOLOv5 are deployed in context from fruit detection on outdoor images (apples and mangoes).
  - The two models achieved on-par state-of-the-art results attaining 93% and 88% F1 score for mango and apple images, respectively... more information in GitHub.
- 2. Reviews Classification | Skills: Web scraping, Sklearn, machine learning algorithms
  - $\circ$  This project involves scraping over 200k reviews using Scrapy and classifying them as positive or negative using different Sklearn models. Also, dealing with the issue of data imbalance.
  - o SVM classifier was the best in this application achieving an F1 score of 89%... the code is in this GitHub repo.
- 3. Crop Disease Classification | Skills: Python, TensorFlow and Keras, Computer Vision
  - This is classification problem applied to Agriculture. This project was presented as a solution to a Zindi Challenge and ranked as top 15% solution...more information in GitHub.

#### **Award and Honors**

**Golden Key Award**, for being among the top 15% academic performers among the 2019 cohort. (2020-2022)

**African Institute for Mathematical Sciences(AIMS) Scholarship**, for MSc Mathematics at S.U (2019-2010)&(2020-2021)

**Award for Excellence**, African Institute for Mathematical Sciences(AIMS)

(Jan 2019- Nov 2019)

Vice-Chancellor's Academic Award, the best student in Bachelor of Science (Statistics option)

(2014/2015, 2015/2016 and 2016/2017 academic years)

**First place**, Mathematics contest with 1954 contestants (2012)

# **Groups and Societies**

- Computer Vision and Remote Sensing Group at Technische Universität Berlin, Germany [1]
- Data Science Research Group at African Institute for Mathematical Sciences, South Africa [1]
- Golden Key International Honour Society
- Kenya National Society of Statisticians

## **X** Hobbies and Interests

- Volunteering and Charity work.
- Playing puzzle games like Rubik's cube and Sudoku game.
- Reading books. Currently reading "The Compounding Effect" by Darren Hardy.

**Declaration**: I hereby declare that the information furnished above is true (**Sunday 4**<sup>th</sup> **June, 2023 at 00:41**).

Koch f

Kiprono Elijah Koech